<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Honest, vpright, faithful, and plain dealing with thee O army of the common-wealth (so called) without flattery, in true unfeigned love to thee with something more particularly unto the officers of the army, and those that join with them in the outward government of this nation : wherein truth, uprightness, and equity is declared for, and deceit, wickedness, oppression, and tyranny is declared against / by one who loves the prosperity of truth, and the good and well-being of all creatures, George Fox the younger.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2005A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17061371</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17061371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105855</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40340)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105855)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1616:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Honest, vpright, faithful, and plain dealing with thee O army of the common-wealth (so called) without flattery, in true unfeigned love to thee with something more particularly unto the officers of the army, and those that join with them in the outward government of this nation : wherein truth, uprightness, and equity is declared for, and deceit, wickedness, oppression, and tyranny is declared against / by one who loves the prosperity of truth, and the good and well-being of all creatures, George Fox the younger.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, d. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105855:1"/>
            <p>Honeſt, Vpright, Faithful, AND PLAIN DEALING With Thee O ARMY OF THE COMMON-WEALTH OF ENGLAND (So called) Without flattery, in true unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Love to thee.</p>
            <p>With ſomething more particularly unto the Officers of the ARMY, and thoſe that join with them in the outward Government of this Nation.</p>
            <p>Wherein Truth, Uprightneſs, and Equity is declared for, and Deceit, Wickedneſs, Oppreſſion, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny is declared againſt.</p>
            <p>By one who loves the proſperity of Truth, and the good and well-being of all creatures, <hi>GEORGE FOX</hi> the younger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the
<hi>Bull</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105855:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105855:2"/>
            <head>Honest, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, Faithful, and Plain Dealing, with thee O Army, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T your firſt going forth, there was a true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Principle which ſtirred in the hearts of many of you, which convinced you of ſin in the particular, and it alſo ſhewed you the deſperate wickedneſs, cruelty, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and oppreſſion which was upheld by unjuſt and unrighteous Laws and Rulers, whereby the honeſt people were much oppreſſed, and in ſeveral of you there aroſe a true zeal againſt this abomination, and then I know your lives, and what you had was not dear to ſome of you, but was freely given up to do your Nation ſervice in breaking down that oppreſſion and tyranny which was brought upon it by the Enemies of God, and it; and then a mighty courage and boldneſs aroſe in many of you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt oppreſſion and oppreſſors, and the Lord appeared with you againſt them, becauſe they were his Enemies, and ſought to deſtroy the very appearance of truth; and then many of you were low and tender, and the hearts of ſuch people as had honeſt deſires in them, and breathed for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, they were much affected with you, and the cauſe you declared for, and vowed and engaged to be true and faithful unto, and then the Lord appeared with you in the field, giving you mighty Victories over your Enemies, that ſo he might make way for his living truth to be ſpread, which was then ſtirring in his people; and the Lord vveak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Enemies before you, and ye ſavv his mighty hand therein, and his mighty Work (in overturning thoſe his Enemies) proſpered in your hands (for he made you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments therein) until he had ſcattered his Enemies, and then he gave you povver and opportunity to accompliſh that you had vovved and engaged to do, and vvhich his light in your hearts had ſhewed you, that you ought to have done.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105855:3"/>
            <p>But you not keeping to that which firſt appeared in you, and made you ſenſible of the oppreſſion that was upheld by the unrighteous Laws, Lawyers, and Rulers; an earthly ſelfiſh ſpirit, got up in many of you, which exceedingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed covetouſneſs and pride in you; and then the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your pay, and the ſpoile of your enemies, and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs, and the fulneſs of the creatures began to be more delightful to many of you, then the liberty you once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for; and then ſome among you began to ſee how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and hypocriſie crept in amongſt you, and appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; but you whoſe hearts went after your covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſelf-ſeeking, ſoon ſtopt them, either by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, or by advancing them into greater places, or by turning them out of the Army; and thus you began to back-ſlide, and then deceit began to wax ſtrong among you, and ſeveral of you began to ſettle your ſelves in the earth, and in your Enemies Eſtates, and then you little regarded the oppreſſion that others ſuffered under, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at eaſe your ſelves; and thus the Enemy beguiled you, and deceit wrought in you, even as it did amongſt ſome of the Sects and Opinions; for in many of them there was a true Principle of God ſtirring once, which convinced them of their own ſins, and alſo ſhewed them the cruelty, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and deceit of the Biſhops and Prelates, and others, and cauſed them to witneſs againſt ſuch; but they not keeping to the meaſure of God in them, a worldly, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, deceitful ſpirit increaſed in them, and then they ſoon began to ſettle themſelves in another form, (without the life and power of God) which was as bad in the nature and ground of it, as that they had witneſſed againſt, only it had another Name.</p>
            <p>And in the ſame manner have ye acted; for ye going from the meaſure of God in you, which ſhewed you the cruelty of the oppreſſors, vvhich ye had fought againſt; ye ſoon began to ſettle the ſame thing in the nature and ground of it, among your ſelves, which you had fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt in others, onely (in deceit and hypocriſie) you gave it another Name.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105855:3"/>
            <p>And then truly great Wickedneſs encreaſed among you, (which made the heart of the righteous ſad) even the ſame as abounded among your Enemies, (which God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrew for their Wickedneſs) yea, for then many of you ran into hunting, hawking, bowling, Horſe-racing, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and other vain Games, and Sports, and Luſts, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and Pride, both in your Dyet and Apparel; and your behaviour was grown ſo lofty, (many of you) that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a burthen to all honeſt-hearted people, who once had an honeſt love going forth towards you; but this your Wickedneſs cauſed their love to wax cold towards you, and many who were your true friends, became aſhamed of you becauſe of your backſlidings.</p>
            <p>And you raiſed up the ſpirit of enmity and bitterneſs in your Enemies more and more againſt you, by theſe things which you ran into; yea, you gave them great advantage by your back-ſlidings, and ſome of you ſaw theſe things many times with Gods Witneſs; but ye not keeping to Gods Witneſs in you, deceitful fears aroſe in you, which ſtopt the mouth of truth in you, when you ſhould have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed againſt the Wickedneſs that was amongſt you; and your fears was, leſt you ſhould have been turned out of your places, and upon this account deceit was grovvn ſo ſtrong among you, and treachery, that ye durſt not ſpeak your minds one to another, for fear ye ſhould be betrayed one by another, and ſo turned out of your places: And thus deceit and a ſlaviſh ſpirit poſſeſt ye, even till you had loſt your Dominion and Authority over your Enemies, &amp; then many of you became afraid to do that vvhich vvas juſt (many times) leſt your Enemies ſhould be more diſpleaſed with you; and in deceit ye bowed, (many of you) even to your Enemies, and ſought more to pleaſe them, then to do that you had engaged to do; &amp; then you turned out many of your friends, and took in many of your Enemies, and mixed your ſelves with them; yea, you turned out many of your faithful friends, onely for coming into the life and obedience of that which many of you profeſſed in words, and pretended once that you fought for the liberty of.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105855:4"/>
            <p>O ARMY! this is plain truth to thee, vvithout flattery; and thus falſhood overſpread you, until the honeſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that once ſtirred in you, was almoſt deſtroyed, and then ye little regarded the ſufferings of the innocent, nor the oppreſſion that vvas in the Land, but ye rather ſought to eſtabliſh yourſelves in the honor &amp; fulneſs of this World; but (poor creatures!) ye could not ſettle your ſelves in a peace there, for your Enemies daily plotted againſt you, &amp; had it not been juſt vvith the Lord to have ſuffered your Enemies to have deſtroyed you, becauſe of your grievous back-ſlidings and wickedneſs? O conſider it, conſider it while ye have time, and prize the Lords loving kindneſs that he ſhould yet ſpare you, and yet give you time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the Lord hath ſhewed you your backſlidings, with his eternal Witneſs in you, and hath begun to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the deſigns of thoſe that vvould have cut you off in your backſlidings; and ye confeſs (ſome of you) that you are vvilling to take ſhame alſo to your ſelves wherein you have back-ſlidden; therefore ſeeing it is thus, all mind that of God in you, which ſheweth you your back-ſlidings, and believe, and wait in that, to feel that nature judged and deſtroyed in you, wherein all this Wickedneſs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit hath lodged; and keepe in the fear and dread of the Lord God, that ſo ye may receive his pure Wiſdom, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ye may be ordered in the particular, &amp; that ye in Gods Wiſdom and Fear may come to rule (in your places) for God, to be a terror to evil-doers, and an encouragement to them that do well.</p>
            <p>And take heed of a ſelfiſh, earthly ſpirit in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and of the honor, and glory, and gain of the World, (for that the Lord is againſt;) Oh! there is a ſtrong, deep root of it in many of you, which the Spirit of Judgement and burning, and the Ax of God is to deſtroy; therefore wait to feel its Work in you.</p>
            <p>O ARMY! in thee was I ſeveral years together, in which time I ſaw the mighty appearance of God with thee, even in the time of the outward War; and when the War vvas <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105855:4"/>ended, I left thee, in obedience to the appearance of the living God unto me, who called me out of thee by his powerful Word in my heart, through which he hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified me, and hath brought me into the life of that truth, which I, and many of you in the Army profeſſed in Words.</p>
            <p>And I can truly ſay in the fear of the Lord, That my love hath been, and yet is tender towards you, for the good of your ſouls; and I have ſeen your conditions, and hath conſidered them in the ſpirit of the Lord, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not flatter any of you, but muſt deal plainly and and truly with you and all people.</p>
            <p>Truly in many of you there is an exceeding lofty, proud, covetous, deceitful nature; and in others of you there is a lofty, proud, luſtful, devouring, wanton, vain nature; though many of you I know have felt a meaſure of the power of God, yet verily ye have ſo back-ſlidden, that iniquity hath gotten a ſtrong hold and root in moſt of you; that ſo ye muſt keep down to the Witneſs of God in you, which ſearcheth your hearts, and will let you ſee what is there, that ſo the Lord's righteous Judgement ye may all feel it, and own it upon that nature in you which is contrary to the living God; for if ye keep not to the ſpirit of Judgement, I know whatever ye have declared in words, that a ſelfiſh ſpirit will get up more and more to act in you; and verily friends, if you keep not your minds to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the pure God in you, a ſecret boaſting will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to get up in you, of what you have done, and then you will ſoon forget where you are, and your minds will run further and further into your Commiſſions, and into your great Houſes and Lands, which many of you have got; and others minds will run into your Souldiers places, and eaſe, and idleneſs, and theſe things will beguile you if you take not heed, &amp; you will ſoon forget the oppreſsions, then, that others ſuffer under; and if ye ſhould do thus, verily the Lord God would ſoon overturn you, &amp; break you to pieces.</p>
            <p>Therefore all wait in the light which ſhews you ſin and evil, that ſo by it ye may be brought to deny your ſelves, <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105855:5"/>and to come out of the loftineſs that ye have been in, into the true humility, (which goes before the true honor) and come into moderation both in your Dyet and Apparel, &amp; in all things, &amp; this would anſwer the Witneſs of God in people; and that being anſwered, it would beget again a love in them towards you, which you loſt when you went into the exceſs. Therefore be ſober, and watch in the light of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which he hath enlightened you withall, and believe in it, that ſo ye may be preſerved by it, out of the deceitfulneſs of this World, and that ye may be kept faithful in your places for the preſerving of the outward peace and liberty of the Nation, while ye feel a freedom in that which convinceth you of evil, for the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a carnal Weapon; &amp; know the manifeſtation of God's Spirit in you, and wait to feel the motions of it, and be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient thereto, and this will bring you to do violence to no man, nor to accuſe any falſly; but it will bring you out of all ſuch things, if you keep to it, and it will make you to be content with ſuch wages as may find you food and rayment, and things neceſſary and convenient for your places, and this you would then be worthy of.</p>
            <p>So know the Lord hath a mighty Work to do, therefore wait in his light, that ye may be kept truly ſenſible of your places, and go not beyond them, but keep in the fear of the Lord, and wait to know what God requireth of you in your places, leſt the Lord caſt you out. So remember you are warned, and it is in tender love to your ſouls.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This following, more particularly concerneth the Officers of the Army, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Rulers of this Nation, then the Army in general.</head>
               <p>Take heed of raiſing or continuing War with other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (in your own wills) for to get your ſelves a Name, and to get their earthly Treaſures, as ſome of you have been inſtruments to do, for the Lord's hand hath been, and yet is againſt that, and he will not proſper you therein; therefore be you warned, and know that this is a warning unto you from the Lord God; and ſeek peace, and eſchew evil, and learn to do well, that the bleſsing of the Lord ye may come to feel, and that this deſtroying of creatures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105855:5"/>Religion, and the honor &amp; gain of this World may ceaſe.</p>
               <p>And take heed how ye meddle with Religion, for that hath ſplit &amp; broken many Rulers before you; therefore ſet not up one ſect, and throw not down another by an outward law &amp; force, for that is wrong, &amp; the Lord is againſt that; but wait in his light to receive his counſel, that ſo ye may be kept in Gods Wiſdom, &amp; that therein ye may be inſtruments in the hand of the Lord, for the keeping of the outward peace of theſe Nations which are under your command.</p>
               <p>And take heed of hearkening unto ſuch who in the kings time cryed him up, &amp; ran to him to give them a law to ſettle them in their Worſhip; &amp; then again in the Parliaments time ran to them &amp; cryed them up, begging a Law to ſettle Church-government, (as they call'd it) &amp; then in the late Protectors time cryed them up, &amp; petitioned unto them with many feigned flattering words, and begged a law of them to ſettle them in their Worſhip; now theſe are the deceitful workers, who teach for filthy lucre, &amp; are time obſervers, who through covetouſneſs and feigned words, makes merchandize of the people; &amp; theſe quench the ſpirit, and deſpiſeth propheſying, and changeth with the times &amp; Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, let them be never ſo contrary, and theſe are neither true to God nor man, but are men pleaſers, and ſuch ſerves not the Lord Jeſus, but their own bellies; and theſe wanting the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, runs to the Rulers for an outward power to uphold them; theſe are whored from the life of God in their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and theſe ſeek to ſtop the life of God where-ever it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears; therefore take heed of upholding or ſetting them up by an outward Law, leſt you become the beaſt [mark that] which carrieth the Whore, which is to be taken with the falſe Prophet and the old Dragon, (the Father of all unrighteouſneſs) and caſt alive into the Lake.</p>
               <p>Now the true Worſhip and Religion which ſtands in the ſpirit, and in the truth, muſt be ſet up, and eſtabliſhed, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by the Power immortal, and not by an outward Law.</p>
               <p>But let your Law ſtop that in all (where-ever it appears) which wreſtles with fleſh and blood, and fights with the creature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion; for this ſpirit could never make manifeſt the true Worſhip &amp; Religion, neither would it ſuffer others to do it who <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105855:6"/>had the ſpirit of God, if it could ſtop them by an outward Law or force; ſo that which fights, wreſtles, and ſtrives with the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures about religion, is not for Chriſt, but is <hi>ante</hi> againſt Chriſt &amp; the Apoſtles, who wreſtled not with fleſh &amp; blood, but with the power of darkneſs, &amp; with the ſpiritual wickedneſs in high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſo wickedneſs &amp; deceit might be deſtroyed in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and that the creatures might be preſerved; and their Weapons were not carnal, but ſpiritual.</p>
               <p>But they that cryes out to the Rulers for an outward Law to uphold their worſhip &amp; religion, they war not with the ſpiritual Weapons, but with the carnal, and theſe deſtroys the creatures, but cannot deſtroy the wickedneſs; &amp; theſe have quenched the ſpirit in their own particulars, and theſe would quench it in others, &amp; will not ſuffer him that hath ſomething revealed unto him, to ſpeak, but cryes to the Magiſtrates, or to the rude multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, for help, and ſo flees to their carnal Weapons, and thoſe being ſtirred up by their Teacher, ſome of them oft times beats thoſe that have the truth to declare in their Synagogues, &amp; hales them out, &amp; railes on them, &amp; ſpits upon them, and ſometimes buffets, ſtocks, whips, &amp; impriſons, and mangles the creatures, &amp; ſo mars &amp; defaceth the workmanſhip of God; and this hath been the work of Antichriſt in all ages when Truth hath appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deceit; and ſuch cannot truly ſay, truth hath prevailed on their parts, when they have thus beaten, and haled, and ſtocked, and whipped, and impriſoned the creatures; but violence there at that time hath prevailed, by which they that have had the truth to declare, oft times have been ſtopped from ſpeaking it.</p>
               <p>So let none do violence to one anothers perſons or eſtates, but let your Law take hold on them that would do ſo but let them alone in their profeſſion, and then it will ſoon appear who is in the truth, and who are Miniſters of Chriſt, and of the ſpirit; for thoſe that are in the ſpirit of truth, will aſſuredly prevail over them that be in the ſpirit of deceit; and this will be manifeſted ſoon, if there be no violence done to them who be in the ſpirit of truth, thereby to ſtop them from ſpeaking the truth, and then the truth wil reach unto the Witneſs of God in peoples conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; &amp; then many who could not diſcern the Truth whiles there was ſuch ſtrivings &amp; fightings with the creatures, wil come to ſee <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105855:6"/>and feel it; and then Truth ſhall prevail, and deceit ſhall fall where ever it be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and what covering ſoever it have got, it ſhall be ript off, and he that is in the Spirit of Truth, and abides in it, ſhall overcome all falſe ſpirits.</p>
               <p>Now I know ye are not altogether ignorant, how that the lives and goods of ſeveral in this Nation hath been made a prey upon by the Prieſts, who hath robbed and ſpoyled both the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs, Widows, &amp; others; &amp; hath priſoned ſeveral unto death by a Law made by the Popiſh Kings, and ſince ſtrengthened by thoſe that are called Proteſtants, concerning tythes, &amp; theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned hath ſuffered thus for not paying tythes. Now tythes in the Law given by the command of God unto <hi>Levi</hi> the changeable Prieſthood, (who was to have no inheritance among his Brethren) was for the maintenance of that Tribe, &amp; alſo for the Fatherleſs, the Widows, and the Strangers; but Chriſt being come after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> he is the everlaſting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable High-Prieſt, not made by a carnal commandment, but by the power of an endleſs life; he offering himſelf up once for all, put an end to the changeable prieſthood, who were made by a Law which gave them tythes; ſo this Prieſthood &amp; this Law was changeable, this Prieſthood could not continue by reaſon of death; ſo this Prieſthood being changed &amp; ended by Chriſt the unchangeable Prieſt, made by the power of an endleſs life, there was a neceſſity alſo of a change &amp; end of that law by which the changeable Prieſts (who could not continue by reaſon of death) were made, which gave them tythes; then Chriſt the everlaſting High-Prieſt, made by the power of an endleſs life, by the ſame power he made Miniſters, &amp; freely gave them gifts for the work of the Miniſtry, which was for the perfecting of the Saints; &amp; in the power of an endleſs life ſent he them forth, ſaying, <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give, and into what houſe ſoever ye enter, and they receive you, ye may eat ſuch things as are ſet before you, for the workman is worthy of his meat.</hi> Theſe were Workmen, &amp; they firſt planted a Vinyard, &amp; then eat of the fruit thereof; firſt gathered a flock, &amp; then eat of the milk thereof; ſowed ſpiritual things, &amp; reaped of their carnal things unto whom they had ſown ſpirituals; preached the Goſpel, &amp; lived of the Goſpel; theſe were not made Miniſters by the will of man, nor by an outward Law, neither <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105855:7"/>received they their maintenance by an outward Law, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled or forced any to pay them; neither robbed, or ſpoyled, or impriſoned they any that would not give them maintenance; but they had a neceſſity laid on them to preach the Goſpel, and they did ſo, and coveted no mans gold, nor ſilver, nor apparel; &amp; theſe ſought not peoples goods, but them; &amp; their diligence and care was not to make the Goſpel chargeable, for having food &amp; rayment, they were therewithall content; &amp; they received it of ſuch alſo (mark that) as did receive them and their teſtimony, and ſo oppreſſed no man.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Paul</hi> foreſaw that after his departure grievous &amp; raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wolves ſhould enter, that would not ſpare the flock; &amp; Chriſt propheſied of them alſo; and theſe entered before
<hi>John's</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and he warned the little children (who had the annointing abiding in them) to take heed of them, for they were the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, and went from the annointing in the particular, and ſo from thoſe that were in it; &amp; then the murthering ſpirit got up in theſe, &amp; the World went after theſe who ſpared not the flock, but killed thoſe that had the teſtimony of Jeſus, which is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Propheſie; &amp; theſe Antichriſts having loſt the ſpirit, being ravened from it in their own particulars, and having killed thoſe that were made Miniſters by the ſpirit, who had freely received, &amp; freely gave; then they ſet up their Schools &amp; Colledges, there to make Miniſters by the wil of man, &amp; then made a carnal Law, whereby they had tythes given them; for theſe had not freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, neither would they freely give; ſo tythes among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles was ſet up by the devouring, murthering ſpirit by a law by which law they are yet upheld, (&amp; not by God) &amp; they that yet receive the tythes, are found in the devouring, murdering ſpirit, (many of them) who have devoured many peoples goods in this nation, who could not for conſcience ſake pay tyths, &amp; hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſeveral others to be kept in priſon until death for the ſame: And this hath been the work of Antichriſt, who hath the ſheeps clothing, the good words, but inwardly is the ravening Wolf.</p>
               <p>And in this Work many of the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> hath been found of late, as is manifeſt by their fruits; &amp; they have the ſame unjuſt law to oppreſs &amp; deſtroy the innocent ſtil, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome of you have pretended and declared much to the contrary long.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105855:7"/>
               <p>Now many of the Prieſts when we tel them of this their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; oppreſſion, they will ſay, <hi>They are Miniſters of the Goſpel, &amp; he that preaches the Goſpel, God hath hath ordained that he ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> Well, we ſay ſo too, <hi>That we are Miniſters of the goſpel, &amp; he that preaches the goſpel, ought to live of the goſpel (which is the power of God) and ought not to have any outward Law to compel any to give him whereon to live.</hi> So this is that which we (who have learned to do unto all men, as we would they ſhould do unto us) would have, that he that preaches the goſpel ſhould live of the goſpel, and not on that which comes by the force of an outward Law; but the Prieſts maintenance is contrary to the maintenance of the Miniſters of the Law or Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Therefore, firſt let there be no outward Law to hinder or reſtrain any people from hearing any whom they believe is a Miniſter of the Goſpel, nor yet to compel any to hear any one vvhom they believe is not a Miniſter of the Goſpel; for an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Law can but reſtrain or compel the outward man, but the heart none can reſtrain from evil, nor compel to the good, but the Law &amp; Power of God only in the heart; therefore let there be a free liberty for all people to meet concerning their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, provided that under pretence of meeting to worſhip, they meet not to plot for the overthrowing of the outward Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors by an outward power, for if that can be proved and made manifeſt, truly then let ſuch ſuffer by an outward Law.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe, let there be no law to compel any one to maintain any Teacher, neither let there be any law to reſtrain any one from giving any thing to their Teacher, (for this is but equal) ſo let the people have liberty herein, that ſo this oppreſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the maintenance of Teachers may ceaſe; And then it will ſoon appear whether theſe Prieſts be Miniſters of the Goſpel, and whether their Goſpel will maintain them, yea, or nay.</p>
               <p>But many of the Rulers have ſaid, <hi>If we ſhould not provide maintenance for our Miniſters, then preaching would ſoon fall, and then many people would become heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, He that is a Miniſter of Chriſt, the Power of God, which is the everlaſting Goſpel, neceſſity is laid upon him to preach the Goſpel, and wo be unto him if he preach not the Goſpel: And he that is ſent forth by Chriſt, is not to take <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105855:8"/>thought what he ſhall eat, or what he ſhall drink, or wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all he ſhall be clothed, for his heavenly Father knoweth that he hath need of all theſe things, and provides them for choſe that he ſends forth, (without an outward Law to compel it) that ſo they lack not any thing.</p>
               <p>Now that Miniſtry which the forcing an outward mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for it, will uphold it, &amp; the not forcing an ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ward main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for it, will cauſe it to ceaſe, [mark] this Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>try never did any good or ſervice for God, not never can (that is God's truth unto you) at the furtheſt; this Miniſtry hath but brought people to draw near unto God with their mouths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to appear to honor him with their lips, when their hearts have been afar off; but this Miniſtry could never bring any into the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and Chriſt, whom God hath ſent and freely given for a Covenant of light; and without this knowledge, all people upon the earth are without the life eternal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo are heathens, whatever they profeſs in words, though they may make long prayers, and think to be heard in their much ſpeaking, as the phariſees &amp; hypocrites did, whom Chriſt call'd Heathens; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider what a Miniſtry you have upheld, and do uphold.</p>
               <p>So let that Miniſtry fall which cannot ſtand without an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Law for to compel an outward maintenance for it, for the Lord regards it not, but his hand is againſt it, and againſt that which would uphold it, and both muſt fall together.</p>
               <p>So what is here declared concerning Religion, and the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Teachers, and the like, it is in the equal royal Law of liberty, which is, To love thy neighbor as thy ſelf, and to do unto all as we would be done unto.</p>
               <p>And ſo if the ſpirit which we are led and guided by (who are called in ſcorn <hi>Quakers</hi>) be not able to prevail over that vvhich vve oppoſe in others as error, then let us be manifeſted to be in the error, and let us fall; onely let there be a fair tryal, and let there not be ſuch beating, and haling, &amp; tearing, and mangling, and ſtocking, and impriſoning of the creatures as hath been; for vvhere theſe things have been acted, many have been ſtopped at that time for ſpeaking the truth, yet notvvithſtanding the truth hath prevailed over all, and ſhall prevail. And if that can be proved againſt us truly, that we plot at our Meetings, or at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105855:8"/>any other time againſt the outward Governors, to overturn them by an outward power or force; then let us alſo ſuffer (as I ſaid before) by a juſt Law.</p>
               <p>And if he that ſends us forth, will not provide food and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for us, then let us want; and if we cannot live of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel which we preach, without an outward Law to compel us an outward maintenance, &amp; if our Miniſtry will not ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, then let us want whereon to live, &amp; let our Miniſtry fall.</p>
               <p>And let none be compelled to uphold another's Meeting-place (concerning their Worſhip) for that is oppreſſion; but let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one uphold their own; and that ſort of profeſſors that will not uphold the place where they meet to worſhip, let their houſe fall, and then it will appear where the earthly ſpirit lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth; for they that compel others to uphold another's place of Worſhip, doth but cover and ſtrengthen the earthly ſpirit; therefore let there not be ſuch havock made of peoples goods as hath been of late upon many who could not give to the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding another's Meeting-houſe; for this is out of the equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the oppreſſion and tyranny.</p>
               <p>So come into that which is equal, and keep in that, and that will bring you to act that which is equal and juſt, unto all, and to break all outward Laws that are not equal and juſt, but tends to tyranny and oppreſsion; and truly there are many Laws and Cuſtoms in this Nation, whereby the innocent are oppreſt; ſo wait to feel the power of God, that ye may rule and govern in that, (for the Lord,) and feeling the power of God, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that, it will bring you out of all deceit and tranſgreſsion in the particular, and ſo to ſtand over all deceit and tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the general; and it will alſo bring you to judge righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, without reſpect to perſons; and this will reach to the Witneſs of God in all conſciences.</p>
               <p>So wait to feel the higher power to rule over the evil doer in the particular, &amp; to know &amp; feel the Authority of God there, &amp; then ye wil come to rule over all evil doers in the higher Power, even in the Authority of God, &amp; then that of God in all conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences where ye come to rule, ſhall anſwer to your government.</p>
               <p>But if ye give way to the evil-doer in the particular, and let him have the liberty there, [mark that] then that will cauſe the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105855:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Juſt to ſuffer in the particular, and then the ſame will give way and liberty to evil doers without, whereby the Juſt without will come to ſuffer alſo.</p>
               <p>Therefore keep to the power of the Lord in your own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, (you who have felt it) and that will bring ye to do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice unto all without partiality, &amp; this will make you honorable in the hearts of the people and then ſhall righteouſneſs, Truth; Equity, Mercy, &amp; Juſtice, proſper over all, and be exalted, &amp; all deceit unrighteouſneſs, &amp; unrighteous vvays ſhall be confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So remember, <hi>He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>Something after.</head>
               <p>AND all ye that are Officers and Rulers now, who have taſted of the pure power of the Lord God, and hath felt it ſtirring in you againſt all oppreſſion and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, whereby alſo ye were made to witneſs againſt the back ſlidings of others, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the loſing of your places, (ſome of you) ſome being turned out, and others that could not ſtay for conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>VVell, keep to the power of the Lord which ye have felt, and do not abuſe it, but wait in it, that ye may be kept low in his fear, that ſo thoſe who are come to ſee their back-ſlidings, and do repent them, may come to have unity with you, and you with them, in that which kept you in any meaſure out of the back-ſlidings, and which hath alſo brought them to ſee theirs, and to repent of it; for that is but one in you both, it is even the meaſure of the pure God which is given you to profit withall; therefore in that all wait to receive the wiſdom which is from above, that in it ye may all be preſerved and kept in enity together, and that therein ye may be inſtruments for the ſetling and preſerving the outward Peace and juſt Liberties of the people of theſe Nations, which are under your charge.</p>
               <p>But verily, much of the wars which hath lately been entered into, hath not been for the peace, ſafety, and well-being of theſe Nations, (for the power being loſt, pride and luſt was the ground of them;) Therefore all mind the Lords wiſdom and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, that peradventure ye may find, and ſee a way how to ſtop them, leaſt ye bring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies upon heaps both upon your ſelves and theſe Nations; for yet verily, breaking, breaking, overfurning, and yet overturning will be among all thoſe that will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the counſel of the Lord, and wait in his light, to be led and guided in his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; for he will be known to rule in the kingdoms of men, and he will exalt his own Name over all.</p>
               <p>Many are your Enemies within and without, therefore be not high-minded, but fear, leaſt they prevail over you.</p>
               <p>The Lord is near unto all thoſe that fears him, and truſts in his Name, to deliver them; but thoſe that go out of his fear, and truſts in the wiſdome or arm of fleſh, they ſhall be broken; the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given forth
<date>in the former part of the 3d. Month,
1659.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
